## Ronny Litvack-Katzman

5240 Avenue Casgrain • Montréal, QC • H2T 1W9 • Canada ronny.litvack-katzman@mail.mcgill.ca • 647.519.1536

#### **Personal Statement**

I have a broad training in the applied natural sciences in addition to a comprehensive background in English Literature. I have researched and written on a variety of periods and forms, from the Middle Ages to the twentieth century, from drama to poetry to fiction as well as literary theory. My research focuses on questions of narratology and epistemology and their intersections, with a specific focus on the science fiction of the long nineteenth century and its influence on/from the natural sciences. My current research explores formal, rhetorical, and narratological links between Darwinian evolution and the science fiction of H.G. Wells in his scientific romances (1895-1904) and writings for science education. I have developed other critical teaching, research, journalistic, and editorial skills, in my role as a research and teaching assistant and as Editor of the Science and Technology section at *The McGill Tribune*.

### **Education**

2021-Pres. MA in English, McGill University.

2017-2020 BA & B.Sc. in English Literature and Biology, McGill University.

—. Independent Research Study (Paper: "Knowledgeable Practice and the Practice of Knowledge: Epistemic Anxieties and the Creation of Scientific Images in Nineteenth Century Science Fiction"), supervised by Prof. Michael Nicholson (Department of English) and Prof. Lauren Chapman (Department of Biology).

# **Technical Proficiencies/Languages**

Natural Languages

English (Fluent)
French (Basic)

Middle English (1100-1400) (Basic)

Computing Languages

R (Proficient)

# **Work Experience**

2022-Pres. Research Lead ('Ciphers of the Times' Research Project), McGill University

Library, Rare Books and Special Collections (ROAAr), Montreal, QC

2021-2022 — Research Assistant

2021-2022	Teaching Assistant (SOCI 210: Sociological Perspectives), McGill University,
	Department of Sociology, Montreal, QC
2021-2021	Editorial Assistant, JMIR Publications, Toronto, ON
2020-2021	Editor, Science and Technology, <i>The McGill Tribune</i> , Montreal, QC
2018-2020	—. Staff Writer
2017-2018	—. Contributor
2019-2021	Grant and Proposal Writer, McGill University Health Centre and RI-MUHC,
	Montreal, QC
2019-2021	Undergraduate Research Assistant, Chapman Lab, McGill University, Montreal,
	QC

### **Volunteer Positions**

2022-Pres	Project Organizer, McGill Science and Technology Studies Working Group,
	Montreal, QC
2021-2022.	M.A. Graduate Curriculum Representative, English Graduate Students Association
	(EGSA), Montreal, QC
2018-2020	Vice President (Fundraising and Outreach), HOSA McGill, Montreal, QC
2018-2019	Director of Event Logistics, National Integrative Research Conference, Montreal,
	QC

## **Awards**

2022	Hugh MacLennan Fellowshi	n for the Study of English	McGill University \$1000
2022	Trugii Wachellian I enowsin	p for the study of English	, wicom om versity, wrood

- 2022 Graduate Mobility Award, McGill University, \$2500
- Joseph-Armand Bombardier Canada Graduate Scholarships Program Master's Scholarships (CGS-M), McGill University, \$17,500
- Viola Whitney Pratt Memorial OSOTF Scholarship in English (Declined), University of Toronto, \$7500
- 2021 Entrance Scholarship (Declined), English MA Program, University of British Columbia, \$5000
- 2020 Chapman Undergraduate Research Award, McGill University, \$2500
- 2019 Science Undergraduate Research Award (SURA), McGill University, \$7500
- 2018 Tomlinson Engagement Award for Mentoring (TEAM), McGill University, \$300

### **Referred Publications**

- June 2021 "'All stories belong to tomorrow': Imagined Communities and the Promise of Futurity in Ngugi wa Thiong'o *Detained*". *The Channel: Department of English Undergraduate Review*, vol. 14, 2021.
- Apr 2021 "Confronting Time in Liminal Space: Placing Queer Identity in Radclyffe Hall's 'Miss Ogilvy Finds Herself". *The Channel: Department of English Undergraduate Review*, vol. 14, 2021.
- Mar 2019 "Representations of Temporality in the Narrative of the Fragmenting Family." *The Channel: Department of English Undergraduate Review*, vol. 12, 2019.

## **Select Non-referred Publications**

Oct 2020 May 2020	"In 'The Invisible Man,' not seeing is believing." <i>McGill Tribune</i> [Montreal, QC]. "How poetry can help us better understand the climate crisis." <i>Terra Observer Magazine</i> [Ottawa, ON].
Feb 2020	"Exploring McGill's scientific archives." (Podcast). <i>McGill Tribune</i> [Montreal, QC], <a href="https://www.mcgilltribune.com/podcasts/exploring-mcgills-scientific-archives/">https://www.mcgilltribune.com/podcasts/exploring-mcgills-scientific-archives/</a> .
Feb 2020	"Conservation in the digital age." <i>McGill Tribune</i> [Montreal, QC], 11 Feb. 2020.
Dec 2019	"The haphazard world of scientific research funding." McGill Tribune [Montreal,
	QC].
Oct 2019	"Testing Darwin's ecological questions." McGill Tribune [Montreal, QC]
Jul 2019	"Biological crisis forces species to adapt or go extinct." McGill Tribune [Montreal,
	QC].
Feb 2019	"Removing the barriers for genetic data sharing." <i>McGill Tribune</i> [Montreal, QC]
Oct 2018	"United Nations stresses climate conundrum." McGill Tribune [Montreal, QC]
Apr 2018	"The universe at odds: Quantum mechanics versus general relativity." <i>McGill</i>
•	Tribune [Montreal, QC].
Sep 2018	"Eager volunteers take to the web in search of spiders." <i>McGill Tribune</i> [Montreal,
1	QC].

## **Creative Work**

- Sep 2021. "Pride Month." Garbage Day Zine, 2021. Poem. pp. 7-9.
- Mar 2021. "Imitations of Birth." *Yolk*, vol. 1, no. 2, 2021, Poem. p. 31.

# **Presentations/Lectures**

2022	"Chaos Untamed: Confronting Epistemic Anxieties in Olga Tokarczuk's <i>Drive</i> Your Plow Over the Bones of the Dead". SCCS Graduate Conference, Queen's
	University, Kingston, Ontario.
2022	"Darwinian Forms: Evolutionary Narratives in H.G. Wells' The Time Machine".
	McGill Novel Workshop - Graduate Colloquium, Montreal, Quebec.
2022	"Finches, Freaks, and Narrative Form: Darwinism and the Science Fiction of H. G.
	Wells". Lecture to ENGL 341: Literature and Science, Montreal, Quebec.
2020	"Cascading effects of fishing pressure on the diet of the predatory Nile perch in
	Lake Nabugabo, Uganda". OSE x Science Undergraduate Society (SUS) Academia
	Week Poster Showcase, Montreal, Quebec.
2019	"Dietary plasticity and community dynamism: The response of Nile perch to short term changes in fishing pressure". Chapman Lab Meeting, Montreal, Quebec.